On February 19th of last year and March
27th of the prior year, I did these uh
summary videos of some of the most
impactful health findings from a reading
and 250 studies. And now let's do it
again. As we hit 500 studies,
technically I've read a lot more, but
these 500 I have detailed notes. And if
you search physionic and type in a study
number, they'll also be categorized for
you. So, instead of me retelling all of
the rationale for the conclusions across
10 health discoveries, I'm going to a
post my study analysis videos in the
description and the pin comment and b
add the study number on screen so that
you can easily type in physionic and
then just add the study number on into a
search engine. One last thing that you
should know for the impatient, you can
skip to the end of this video for the
highlevel takeaways. We wouldn't want
education, nuance, and science getting
in the way of our busy schedules. Let's
get into it. Benefits of weighted vests.
I had the pleasure of interviewing Robin
on her experience using weighted vests
and I married that with the several
studies that have released on the topic
which I discussed in this analysis
primarily focused on metabolism.
However, that was all due to this
fascinating study where in the
researchers discovered that your bone
cells release molecules to signal the
brain when there's added load on them
like a weighted vest. Ultimately, this
leads to the potential metabolism
maintaining effects when losing body fat
that is unlikely to be explained by just
retaining muscle. It was a fascinating
discovery, but I think that there's much
more research that's necessary
considering many of the human studies
are small. The main point here though is
that if you can handle using a weighted
vest, there's certainly health benefit
at least to your metabolism and likely
in other ways that are yet to be
discovered. Collagen peptides for skin
and joints. I think I actually touched
on the skin benefits of collagen
peptides in my last summary video, which
I discussed in more depth here, but I
also recently delved into the research
on collagen peptides for joint health.
There's a good amount to say here, but
the bottom line is that both realms of
research need some work for different
reasons. For the skin, collagen peptides
seem to work, but the study quality is
pretty poor for many of the studies.
Yet, if we limit it to just a few higher
quality studies, there seems to be a
trend toward indicating effectiveness.
In fact, the same is true for joint
health. However, since most studies look
at arthritis, the collagen
supplementation indicated mild benefit.
So, would that still hold true for
people without arthritis? I'm really not
sure. Plus, all the studies on joint
health are industry affiliated, although
not all the skin studies were industry
affiliated. And we also don't have many,
if any, quality studies comparing
against protein, which is an important
comparison. So, I'm left wanting more
and different comparisons, not the same
industry affiliated studies comparing
against the placebo group. Anyway,
plenty more to say, but I'll leave those
for my dedicated analyses. As a
reminder, it'll be linked in the
description and the pin comment. The
main takeaway here is that if you want
more youthful skin, collagen peptides
have enough good independent evidence
indicating that they work. Although, we
don't know if they'd work better than
protein alone. My guess is yes, for
reasons that I explain in my analysis.
On the other hand, joint collagen
peptide supplementation is really a
tossup if you believe a 100% industry
affiliated studies. And even if you do,
is it worth taking collagen peptides on
an average improvement of about 10%.
In the end, my strict does it work or
does it not? The answer is yes. FGF-21,
the longevity hormone. In a recent
analysis, we also I'm saying we as in
you and I, if you've been along for the
physionic journey with me, we went over
how a hormone fibroblast growth factor
21 that our body produces has shown to
directly increase longevity along with
improving liver health, body fat mass,
lean mass, and plenty of other things.
While many of the results were in mice,
there have been human studies that have
paralleled some of the results in mice,
indicating that there is at least some
translation. There's plenty more
research that needs to be done on
FGF-21, but the human research and the
mouse research agree that the way to
stimulate FGF-21 is through protein
restriction. Now, before half of you
send me to the gallows, I'm well aware
there's plenty of evidence that higher
protein diets offer many health
benefits. As I mentioned in my dedicated
analysis, that is still true. In fact,
both can be true. Even so, this research
indicates there can be benefits of a low
protein diet that is still well above
the necessary amounts for life.
Basically, there's two ways to skin a
walnut. Why a walnut? You've never heard
that expression before? Well, that's
because I made it up. I didn't feel like
adding an animal. So, the takeaway here
is that if you wanted your cells to
produce FGF-21, a low protein diet
around 9% of total calories will do
exactly that. One more word, we don't
have data on older individuals or
exercising individuals. So, it's likely
best to wait until we have that data.
But if you're not the exercising type,
you're young, say, let's say younger
than 60 and not dealing with any other
extenduating circumstances, pregnancy as
just one example, this is an option.
Again, more details on all of it in the
linked video. LP little A and heart
disease. So, plaque develops in your
arteries from the accumulation of
cholesterol containing particles called
low density lipoproteins in your
arteries. However, while we focus a lot
on a particular lipoprotein called an
LDL particle, there's a subset of LDL
that has a specific protein attached to
it called an apo lipoprotein A that
makes it especially dangerous because
not only does it get stuck in the lower
layers of the artery easily, it is more
reactive and has multiple offshoot
effects that make it more dangerous. I'm
glossing over a lot, just so you're
aware. I covered extensively in this
analysis, but that specialized LDL
particle is called a LP little A
particle as well. You can probably guess
luckily only a minority of people have
increased levels of LP little A particle
and it's genetically determined.
Unluckily, that minority is still quite
big. It isn't something like five people
out of a million. It's something closer
to 20 to 30% of people have elevated LP
little A. Plenty more to say on it, but
the takeaway here is that if you have a
family history of people dying early
from heart disease in your family, you
are strongly encouraged to get a blood
test done to test your LP little A. It
is not on a routine blood test. You need
to have it ordered specifically, but it
is extremely important to know. If you
don't have a family history, it's still
encouraged, but the urgency may not be
quite as high as someone with a family
history. I go over solutions in my full
analysis as usual linked. Omega-3s for
the heart. Omega-3s are fats,
specifically fats that come from marine
life like algae, fish, and so on. Think
salmon, fish oil, krill oil, etc. In my
previous video of this sort, I covered
omega-3s and their impact on our brain.
This time, I decided to focus on an area
of health. People associate omega-3s
with heart or cardiovascular health.
There are a lot of studies on the topic
and generally my impression has been
that there is pretty good evidence that
omega-3 fats are heart protective.
There's one major concern related to
omega-3s and I'm sure there are others
but this one came to the forefront and
has been assessed in the research.
Essentially, omega-3s are also linked to
a funky heart rhythm called an
arhythmia. Essentially, while there
might be some truth to that, omega-3s
are linked to arrhythmias, the overall
result on cardiovascular death and
cardiovascular harm is still diminished
when consuming omega-3s. So, it all
really depends on circumstance. The
takeaway here should be that omega-3s
have good evidence backing their
effectiveness for cardiovascular health.
However, if you experience arrhythmias
from consuming omega-3s, consider
reducing your intake or possibly
consider consuming fish forms like
salmon, mackerel, herring, and so on
over pill forms. You'd want to consume
fatty fish about two times per week to
get the adequate amount. Oh, and if
you're a vegetarian, there are algae
forms as well. Now, the next topic might
be one of my favorites because to me,
it's laughably bad. That's C15 fats, not
to be confused with the omega-3 fats
that we just went over. I'll have a bit
more to say on this one, and I often
have a lot more to say on all these
topics, but it just doesn't fit in most
of my public content. So, I created a
community where I can upload my entire
library of video study analyses along
with accompanying articles, quick
summaries, a private podcast, live
sessions with me where we discuss the
science together, and much more. I even
have a detailed supplement guide and a
growing list of protocols based on all
the studies that I read. Anyway, if
you're looking for a way to support my
work as I go on to the next 500 studies
and beyond, and you're also looking to
reap the benefits of having complete
access with even more actionable
takeaways and a growing community of
engaged individuals, check out the
Physionic Insiders. It's linked in the
description. It's the way that I can
fund my work here independent of
sponsorships and minimize perceived
bias. If that's of value to you, again,
the link to join is in the description.
That said, let's get to C-15 FATs, which
is a prime example of why not being
sponsored gives me clearance to say what
I'm about to say next. C15 fats and cell
fragility syndrome.
C-15 fats or by their official name
pentadoninoic acid are a type of
saturated fat that have taken the health
world by storm the last year or so. The
marketing has been strong by a
particular C-15 company and has been
centered around this idea of cell
fragility syndrome which is the idea
that your cell's membranes are
susceptible to damage if they're
deficient in C-15 fats. On the face of
it, that makes some sense because our
cell membrane are made of different
fats. So, I decided to look into the
studies and pulled nine or so studies,
including all the human randomized
control trials that I could find. The
results
made me laugh. Both randomized control
trials, both nonaffiliated to the C-15
company, indicate either no effect or
incredibly small effects on some limited
health measures. And as for what's been
hyped in the marketing, a lot of studies
referenced are cell studies with
improper methodology or correlation
studies that in some cases make cases
against C15 being an essential nutrient.
So in the best case scenario, we have
limited data indicating C15 is actually
important for our cells, at least to the
degree that you need to supplement with
it. And in the worst scenario, it's
mostly hype with the hope that no one
will actually read the studies
referenced. Oh, and by the way, cell
fragility syndrome and many of the cited
studies are produced by the founder or
some researcher employed by a C-15
company or both. I'm open to new
research coming out indicating C-15's
importance, but so far, considering the
certainty by which it's discussed and
hyped, the evidence does not support
C-15 supplementation. Oh, and they did a
clever marketing comparison against
omega-3s trying to signal that C15 is
better than omega-3s. But if you open
the study, the study is absolute trash.
I recommend checking out my video for
the details why I would be embarrassed
as a scientist to publish and then use
such a heaping pile of dung on the basis
for convincing people to spend their
money, especially when omega-3s have
hundreds of studies indicating
effectiveness and C-15 does well not.
So, the takeaway here is don't just
don't. In fact, for one year of C-15,
you could have several years worth of
Physionic Insider Access saving you
money from being wasted on trash
supplements. Is it a shameless plug? No,
because I do feel shame. Deep, deep
shame and remorse, though. It is a plug.
Okay, I promise I'll stop moving on.
Potassium on stroke prevention. Stroke
or the lack of blood flow to the brain
is not good.
Hopefully, you'll trust me when I say
that not getting blood to your brain is
not a good sign of health. To put it
mildly, it's a big and deadly
contributor to cardiovascular disease.
So, I looked over the literature on
potassium intake. And although there
aren't a whole lot of analyses on the
topic, the one that does exist indicates
that potassium intake reduces stroke
risk. And the reason is likely because
potassium reduces blood pressure. In
fact, I also went over a massive human
trial where simply replacing salt with a
little potassium has a significant
effect on reducing cardiovascular
related death. There are of course
cautions like over consuming potassium
can have disastrous consequences and
people with kidney disorders should be
especially careful since your kidneys
regulate the sodium and potassium in
your body. However, one easy takeaway is
that if you use 100% sodium chloride,
like many people do, uh that salt,
consider simply switching it out for a
25% potassium chloride salt. That's the
only change used in the human trial that
I discussed. And that was enough to lead
to a cardiovascular protection. Plus,
apparently that small change is
difficult to notice in the taste
difference since 75% of the salt is
still sodium chloride. That is not the
case at higher concentrations. The best
blood pressure lowering exercise.
There are many probably in the hundreds
of studies that look at exercise's role
in blood pressure. So when we compile
that data into what it's known as a
network metaanalysis, we can do some
pretty nifty comparisons. The end result
is we find out surprisingly which
exercise is best for reducing our
cardiovascular harm. And it's not what
many people might guess. It's not
endurance training. It's not resistance
training, although both are great. It's
actually the wall squat, which I covered
in these videos. The wall squat on
average reduces blood pressure by about
10 points, which is more than some blood
pressure medications. So, the takeaway
here is that if you have high blood
pressure and cleared by your physician,
give the wall squat a shot. About a one
minute work up to it, if you can't get
that one minute for a few sets, two to
three times per week. Multiple
subscribers since those videos released
said that they tried it to great
success. Maybe it'll help you, too.
Curcumin for arthritis. Curcumin is one
of those supplements or phenolic
compounds that has widespread benefits
across the body. I discussed its pretty
impressive blood sugar regulating
effects in the past, but this time I
focused on its anti-inflammatory and
anti-p pain potential for people dealing
with rheumatoid or osteoarthritis.
Again, much like its blood sugar
effects, it seems effective in reducing
pain and improving joint function in
those with arthritis. There are some
nuances that I go into like comparisons
against drugs or compared against other
supplements, but the overall point was
that curcumin has a small effect at
reducing arthritis symptoms and beyond
that may extend the effect across
multiple measurements, including general
inflammation. So, the takeaway here is
that curcumin isn't going to heal you of
arthritis, but it will on average help
reduce the pain and improve the
functionality mildly.
Vilpa.
I didn't involuntarily hiccup. That's an
acronym for vigorous intermittent
lifestyle physical activity. Say it with
me. Vil
you're you're just going to sit there
and let me make a fool of myself.
Vilpas are simply doing everyday
activity like walking, grocery shopping,
alien abduction, climbing stairs, and
the like intensely. Generally, these are
bouts that would last about a minute or
two. So, not very long, but the speed of
which you perform makes the difference.
I went over an analysis where the
researchers determined that even a few
vilpas per day are linked to detectable
reduction in all-c cause mortality. But
that also rang true for cardiovascular
mortality and cancer mortality. The main
point here being that when you're
grocery shopping, up the intensity. So
do the whole carrying as many groceries
at once as you can. Park further away.
When climbing stairs, don't mosy up the
stairs. Climb it like you were a kid,
scared of the dark basement behind you.
If you're an alien, abduct with
intensity. Suck those people up with
purpose. Don't hover. So after all that,
where does that leave us?
Well, for one, I covered 500 studies.
This is only a tiny sample of the
analyzed studies. Aside from that, we
learned weighted vests has some research
indicating that it has a metabolism
protective effect. If you can handle
wearing one for extended periods of
time, it might be worthwhile. Collagen
peptide research has issues, but the
evidence that does exist indicates skin
benefit and mild joint benefits. The
skin benefits are likely the better
reason to use them unless you have
arthritis. FGF-21 is a longevity hormone
that across animal and human studies
shows great promise as being beneficial
for our health across multiple
measurements. To stimulate it in humans,
we merely have to reduce our protein
intake to around 9% of total maintenance
calories. LP little A is a dangerous
subset of particles that is not on a
routine blood test, but should be
checked once in your lifetime,
especially if you have a family history
of heart disease at younger ages. the
40s, 50s, and so on. So, get your LP
little A checked. Omega-3s have pretty
good evidence that they improve heart
health. So, either supplementing with
alcohol oil, fish oil, krill oil, or or
you can simply eat fatty fish, so
salmon, mackerel, etc. a few times per
week. C15 fat supplements have little to
no quality scientific backing. Save your
money and don't fall for the marketing
hype. Potassium protects against
strokes. So, check how much potassium
you consume. And if you use salt on your
food, there's an easy, almost
undetectable change that you can make
that will slash your cardiovascular
risk. Switch your 100% sodium chloride
salt for 25% potassium chloride salt.
The best blood pressure lowering
exercise is the static wall squat.
Curcumin helps combat arthritis,
rheumatoid, and osteoarthritis. And
although the effects are mild, they are
widespread. You can vilpa or vigorously
do dayto-day activities and it will have
a measurable impact on your mortality
risk. Like I said, plenty more to say.
The deeper analyses are linked for you.
But if you're interested in more of my
work summarized, check out this video.
It's 250 studies summarized. If you
click with intensity, you're viling your
way there. I'll see you over there.